Guide to the Henry Phelps Gage papers, 1886-1955.
Gage, Henry Phelps papers, 1886-1955.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Henry Phelps Gage papers, 1886-1955.
1874
Henry Phelps Gage
26 linear ft.
Correspondence, diaries, notes, notebooks, slides, photogrpahs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, diaries, notes on the life of Simon Henry Gage.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Henry Phelps Gage was a physicist and inventor, and son of Cornell University Professor Simon Henry Gage and Susanna Phelps Gage, also a scientist.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, diaries, notes on the life of Simon Henry Gage; notebooks on lectures at Ithaca High School and Cornell University; printed matter on physics and related subjects; slides, photos, photographic plates, and miscellaneous papers. Includes correspondence and other papers pertaining to Henry Phelps Gage's work as head of the Optical Laboratory of Corning Glass Works (1911-1947) and to his membership in various scientific societies; also personal and family correspondence, including papers of Susanna Phelps Gage.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Gage, Henry Phelps.; Gage, Simon Henry, 1851-1944.; Gage, Susanna Phelps.; Cornell University.; Corning Glass Works.; Ithaca High School, (Ithaca, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Optics.; Women scientists.; Physics.
Form and Genre Terms:
Correspondence.; Diaries.; Notebooks.; Color slides.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Miscellaneous
  - Technical Bulletins and Papers (Box 1)
  - Coal Company Reports, 1880's (Box 2)
  - Coal Company Reports, 1880's (Box 3)
  - Technical Bulletins and Papers (Box 4)
  - Technical Pamphlets, Text Books, Lecture Notes (Box 5)
  - Travel Literature, Maps (Box 6)
  - Optics, Glass Manufacturing (Box 7)
  - Technical Papers by Susanna and Simon Gage - Lecture notes, technical pamphlets (Box 8)
  - HPG Block in Morrisville (Box 9)
  - Copy of letters to and from J.G. Schurman from Prof. Gage re dedicating his book on Optic Projection, 1914? (Box 9)
  - Death of Mary Gag-Day, auto accident (Box 9)
  - Carter R. Kingsley (Box 9)
  - Cornell - Gifts to Greater Council Fund, etc. (Box 9)
  - Illuminating Engineering Society (Nomenclature Committee) (Box 9)
  - Birth Certificate (HPG) (Box 9)
  - HPG's Letters - His Philosophy re prejudice, religion (Box 9)
  - Mrs. Theobald Smith (Box 9)
  - Harley Howe (Box 9)
  - Amory Houghton (Box 9)
  - Microscopy in America, attempts at getting it published (Box 9)
  - Spencer Lens Company (Box 9)
- Correspondence
  - Phelps - invented day-light glass, co-author of "Optic Projection," colors of signal lights, Cornell AB - 1908, Ph. D. - 1911, born 1888 (Box 10)
  - Cowan - in charge of optical lab at Corning G.W. retired July 1, 1947 (Box 10)
  - Mrs. Theobald Smith (Box 10)
  - S.H.G.; 1917, 1916, 12-4, re SPG Fdn., 1943 (Box 10)
  - Herbert Lehman re McCarthy, Stanford 1905-1906, Society of Motion Picture Engineers, Optical Society of America, American Association for the Advancement of Science (Box 10)
  - Dr. Mary Gage-Day, 1934 (Box 10)
  - Clara Starrett Gage (Mrs. S.H.G.) (Box 10)
  - Nina W. McCabe (Box 10)
  - William Whitney Gage (Box 10)
  - Copies of Letters to Irving M. Ives, Robert F. Wagner (?) (Box 10)
  - Typewritten account of accident which blinded HPG in one eye, 1935 (Box 10)
  - I.M. Ives, 1952 (Box 10)
  - From HPG to father, 1900 (Box 10)
  - E.L. Mark (Box 10)
  - From Clare Boothe Luce to 1945 re control and development of atomic energy (Box 10)
  - Susanna P. Gage (Box 10)
  - Edward L. Nichols (Box 11)
  - Copies of letters about death of SHG (Box 11)
  - Charles G. Sibley (Box 11)
  - W. Sterling Cole, June 4, 1952 (Box 11)
  - F.D. Roosevelt, Asst. Sec. of Navy, Dec. 15, 1917 (Box 11)
  - Albert C. Durand (Box 11)
  - Mary Gage-Day (Box 11)
  - SHG (Box 11)
  - B.F. Kingsbury (Box 11)
  - 2 copies of resolutions adopted re death of Prof. Edward Leamington Nichols (Box 11)
  - Henry F. Gage (Box 11)
  - George F. Rogalsky (Box 11)
  - W.N. Barnard (Box 12)
  - Phelps to Luella (Box 12)
  - Simon to Susanna (Box 12)
  - Herbert G. Dorsey (Box 12)
  - Albert C. Durand (Box 12)
  - Gage Genealogy (Box 12)
  - Biographical Sketch of Henry Batten, Trustee, 1915 (Box 12)
  - Biographical Sketch of Elizabeth Carse (Box 12)
  - Jared Newman (Box 13)
  - Phelps re Houghton for Congress, May 21, 1918, to Jared Newman (Box 13)
  - Joseph F. Putman (Box 13)
  - F.K. Richtmyer (Box 13)
  - Albert W. Smith (Box 13)
  - Wildeer D. Bancroft (Box 13)
  - A.C. Durand (Box 13)
  - Death of SPH, 1915 (Box 13)
  - Anna Comstock (Box 13)
  - Orchards - Washington (Orondo) (Box 13)
  - Mr. and Mrs. SHG (Box 13)
  - Photostatic copy of "Abstract of Title" for lands of SPG in Morrisville, 1854 (Box 13)
  - Albert H. Gage (Box 13)
  - Edward L. Nichols (Box 13)
  - Tiffany and Company (Box 13)
  - Charles H. Truck (Box 13)
  - Priscilla (to and from) (Box 14)
  - George Washington University (Box 14)
  - Corning Science Club (Box 14)
  - re SHG's "History of Microscopy in America" (Box 14)
  - SHG "Fellowship in Animal Biology" (Box 14)
  - Luzerne Coville (Box 14)
  - Gardner Family Genealogy (Box 14)
  - Settlement of Estate of SHG, Letters of Sympathy (Box 14)
  - D.L. Gamble (Box 14)
  - Copy of letter, Nov. 30, 1955, sending reprints of his Cornell research and thesis to Cornell for the new research library (Box 14)
  - Ruth Sawyer Durand (Box 14)
  - To Lucille Cowan from Beaus' (Box 14)
- Family financial papers and miscellany
  - Letters from Clyde and Edna Gage (Box 15)
  - Estate of Susanna Phelps Gage (Box 15)
  - Letters from Jared Newman (Box 15)
  - Correspondence re William Cowen Estate (Box 15)
  - Printed: "Mary Gage-Day - A Memorial Tribute" (Box 15)
  - Notes on stock quotations, dividends (Box 16)
  - Bills, receipts (Box 16)
  - Sketchbook (Box 16)
  - Bankbooks (Box 16)
  - Check Books (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - Pamphlets on Medicine and Physiology (Box 17)
  - Tax Returns, Ms, Miscellany (Box 18)
  - Class of 1908 - Cornell Material - Given to Archives (Box 18)
  - Copy of Will of SHG (Box 18)
  - Ms. of "Life of SHG" by HPG, 1949 (Box 18)
  - Ms. of "The Spirit of Science," 1904 (Box 18)
  - "Affairs in Cube," John M. Thurston (Box 18)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Magazines (Box 19)
  - Papers and Pamphlets on Physics/Franklin Institute Journals (Box 20)
  - Microscopy, papers on light transmission, Stanford University, Washington Mem. (Box 21)
  - Technical Bulletins and Papers (Box 22)
  - Technical Bulletins and Papers (Box 23)
  - Technical Material on Radio, Sound and Light (Box 24)
  - Technical Papers and Pamphlets (Box 25)
  - Pamphlets on Glass Manufacturing (Box 26)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 27)
- Invitations, programs, family papers and notes
  - Diary, 1951 - HPG; 1949; 1941-1945, etc.; notes 1955 (Box 28)
  - Postcards, 1910-1911 (Box 28)
  - Scrapbook: "History of Henry Phelps Gage, Vol. I," c. 1886-1902 (Box 28)
  - Notebooks (Box 28)
  - Notes on Life of Simon Henry Gage (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous Papers (Box 28)
  - Photogrpahs, Negatives (Box 29)
  - Family Photoraphs (Box 30)
  - Photographs (Box 31)
  - Photographs/Books ( Optic Projection) (Box 32)
  - Photographs, Family Diaries and Accounts (Box 33)
  - Photographs (Box 34)
  - Photographic Plates, Hardware (Box 35)
  - In Manuscript file: Copy of a typescript entitled "Information on the VenTessel Family as related to the Gage Family" (Box 49)